If you want to take term insurance then
this video is definitely for you.  There is a
handy guide that guides you on
which are the best term insurance policies
available.  On the basis of IADA data.
We are making this term insurance video as per the annual report of IADA.
Where we are comparing five term insurance
companies.  On the basis of
their premiums underwritten, what premiums did
they underwrite?  Did you
settle the claim?  What is the solvency ratio?
What are the assets under management?  And
much more.  So, based on those
parameters, we have compared some plans
and made a handy term
insurance video for you.  If you are
looking at term insurance for the first time, then I would
like to brief you a little about what term insurance is.
Term insurance is basically a pure life
insurance.  If you have someone
financially dependent on you or you have any
loans and liabilities, you have any
responsibilities that you have to fulfill in life, then
term insurance is for you.
Ultimate guide to term insurance
is also available on our channel.  Please refer that also
if you are going to take term insurance.
Let's talk about the top five
term insurance companies of 2026.  Let us
compare them on different parameters and
simplify them for you.
[Music]
Quick reminder before we start the video,
if you haven't already, please subscribe to our channel
so that you get the right
information at the right time.  So the five
companies we are comparing are LIC,
ICICI, Axis Max Life, HDFC Life and Tata
AI Life.  Their products are being compared.
LIC has Jeevan Amar, ICICI has
ICICI Pro i Protect Smart Plus,
Axis, Max L Smart Term Plus, HDFC Life
Click to Protect Plus, Tata AI Life
Insurance Sampoorna Raksha Promise.  Let
us talk about this first.  Let's
compare companies before comparing products.
So in Companies we will first talk about
Inception.  Meaning, when did these companies
start?  LIC was incepted on September 1st, 1956.
ICICI was incorporated
on July 20, 2000 and
started operations in the year 2001.  Axis was
incorporated in July 2001 and
started operations in 2002 and became
Axis Max Life Insurance in 2004.
Inception was done in HDFC in August 200.
Tata Life Insurance was incorporated
in August 200 and started operations
in February 2001.  Now let's talk about
how much is the premium under return?  Meaning,
how much premium was collected
by these companies last year.  Talking about LIC,
these 232 companies had underwritten premium worth Rs 475751 crore.
This data is of the last to last year, this
year's IRD report is of 2425.
So let's compare the data of 2324 and 2425
also.  LIC underwrote premium worth ₹48848 crore in 2425.
ICICI had earned Rs 43,235.64 crore last year in 23-24
and Rs 48,950.71 crore this year.
Axis had earned Rs
29,528.97
crore last year and Rs 33,22.60 crore this year.
So you see, the premium has increased.
Premium collection increased.  This means that more
people are becoming aware
about insurance products and they are buying
insurance policies.  HDFC Ltd had
done approximately Rs 63,000 crore last year in 2024
and Rs 71,000 crore this year.
Tata AI had earned Rs 25691
crore last year and Rs 31483 crore this year.  Now let's
talk about assets under management.
Meaning how many assets these companies are managing.
So I have taken the data of 2324 as well as
2425 to show you the comparison.
So the assets under management of LIC were Rs.
4423579 crore in 2024, which
increased to Rs.
crore as on March 31, 2025. ICICI Principal had assets worth Rs. 286000 crore,
which increased to Rs. 33000 crore.
Axis Max Life had Rs. 147000 crore, which
increased to Rs. 171000 crore. HDF FC L had
assets worth Rs. 287000 crore, which increased to Rs.
crore.  Tata AI had
assets worth ₹96,796 crore, which increased to ₹1,23,000
crore as on March 31, 2025.  Now let's talk about the
solvency ratio which
is declared quarterly.  This actually tells
how financially stable the company is.
So we have the solvency ratio quarterly for
March 2024 as well as for March 2025.
LIC's solvency ratio was 1.98 in 2024
and 2.11 in March 2025.
ICICI's was 1.92 and then it
was 2.12 in March 25, Axis's was 1.72 in March 24
, 2.03 in March 25, HDFC's was 1.87 and it was
1.94 in March 25.  Tata IA's
solvency ratio has improved from 1.75 to 1.8, whereas everyone's solvency ratio has improved.
Now let's talk about claims.
So how many claims came and how many were paid?
What is claim settlement ratio?  What
is the amount settlement ratio?  Like this
data has been created from the annual report of IIDA
and there is a handbook
of insurance from it.  So the handbook
of insurance was the old handbook available which was
on 17 February 2025.
So the latest handbook has not come yet.  So the
data we picked up here is of 232.
What we will talk about now is the
data of 232 of the claim settlement ratio of the amount settled.
As soon as the new handbike arrives we will
try to make more videos for you.  So
number of claims that were intimated,
how many claims were intimated in 2324?
crore claims were intimated in LIC.  844312 claims were intimated in LIC
and out of which 82938 were paid,
so the claim settlement ratio will be 98.22. We have done
simple maths and the amount that we are
talking about is what was the amount of 844000 claims that came
and out of which 829000 were approved
?
If we talk about the amount benefit, in 20232 crores,
₹17862
crores was settled against these claims.
So the amount settlement ratio that came out to be
95.18%
means how much premium did they underwrite
?  How much amount did you pay?  What
amount settlement ratio came.  Now we will
also look at ICICI.  Similarly, 13523 claims were
intimated.  Of which 1341 were approved.
So the claim settlement ratio came to 99.17%,
currently the amount of death claims paid in it.
The amount of this is 13400 claims that have been approved, out of which
claims worth ₹166 crore have been approved.
So the amount settlement ratio came to
98.75%.
19638 claims of Axis Max Lef were also intimated.
In which ₹1569 were approved.  99.64%
claim settlement ratio and Rs 1254 crore
approved.  So that
your amount settlement ratio is 97.10%.  Talking about HDFC Click
to Protect Super,
claims were intimated.  Out of this,
19338 claims were made on PA, so HDFC has a
claim settlement ratio of 99.51%.
This is for 2324.  A
claim of Rs 1584 crore was paid.  Against this
₹1338
claims paid.  So your amount
settlement ratio is ₹95.70.  Now let's talk about
Tata.  6431 claims were intimated.   Out
of which 6375 were paid.  So the claim
settlement ratio will be 99.12%
and the amount was Rs 1086.  Claims worth ₹186 crore were
paid against the 6375
policies.  So the amount settlement ratio will be
96.02%.  So this is the financial standing of the company.
How much money came, how much was
given in claims, what is the claim settlement ratio
, what is the amount settlement ratio and
what is the solvency ratio.  Now we will compare these plans on
their benefits, their eligibility
criteria and their premiums.
So the minimum sum assured which
is available in LIC is Rs. 25 lakhs per LIC New Jeevan Number.
The maximum depends on your financial
eligibility.  There is
no maximum limit.
You are given sum assured according to your financial eligibility i.e. income.
[Music] The minimum sum assured in ICICI Pencal is Rs
50.  Minimum sum assured in Axis Max Life
is 25 lakh, HDFC is
50 lakh and Tata Air is 50 lakh.  Then let's talk about
sum assured options.
What are Sum Assured Options?  Meaning you
want the same sum assured throughout.
Suppose you took a policy of Rs 50 lakh.  If you want
my policy to continue for Rs 50 lakh only
, then the sum assured option will be
level sum assured.  Or you want
my policy to keep increasing every year which is called
increasing sum assured option.  LIC has
both.  Both Increasing and Level Sum
Assured options are available.  So
increasing sum assured is helpful for those
where their financial
eligibility is low.  This means that as per the income, the
sum assured available is currently less.  But if they
want to take more cover, then they
take the increasing option so that it will keep
increasing in the future.  When actually needed.
Only Level Sum Assured
is available in ICICI.  Both level and increasing coverages are available in Axis Max Left policy.
Level Sum Assured is available in HDFC and Level Sum
Assured is also available in Tata.  We will talk about the policy term,
how many years minimum and what is the
maximum policy term you can take.  The policy term available
in LIC is minimum 10 years and maximum 40 years.
ICICI
offers term plans ranging from five to 40 years
and whole life policies are also available.   This
means that you can get policy cover for up to 100 years.
10 to 67
years whole life is also available in Axis Max Lef.
5 to 40 years and whole life are also available in HDFC Life.
10 to 67 years and whole
life is also available in Tata AI.  Premium paying term
means for how many years the policy has to be
taken.  For how many years you have to
pay the premium.  So you have the option to
keep it on regular basis.  This means that you should pay
premium for the number of years your policy term is.  This is an
option to either waive the premium within a limited time period
or pay a single premium.
Finish the job by giving it just once.  So
these are the options you have.  So PPT
calls it premium paying term.  So
premium ranging term is available in LIC.
Both regular and limited are available.   This
means you can take a policy for 40 years and if you want, you can
pay the premium for 40 years.  Limited has the
option that you can take it for 5 years less than 40 years or 10
years less.  This means that on a 40-year
policy, you can choose premium paying terms of 35 years and 30 years.
Or
single premium paying option.  [Music] All
three
are available at ICICI, Regular Limited Single.  All three options are available - Regular Limited Single in Axis
, Regular Limited Single in HDFC and
Regular Limited Single in Tata Air.
So you
can choose according to your flexibility whether you should take regular pay or
limited pay.  Minimum and
maximum entry age.  So the minimum entry age
in all is 18 years.  This means that you can
take term insurance only after becoming an adult.
And the main criteria is that you should be
earning.  Meaning, the concept
of term insurance is that if someone
is financially dependent on you or you have some
liabilities which you
want to protect, then you can take term insurance.  The
maximum entry age in all the policies is
up to 65 years, so you can take this policy till the age of 65 years.
Again, whether you will get the policy or not depends on
both financial eligibility and medical eligibility.
Some extra premium will be
charged, it depends on your health.
Premium payment mode means through which mode
you can pay the premium?  You
can pay yearly, half yearly
in LIC, yearly, half yearly, monthly in ICICI,
yearly, half yearly, quarterly, monthly in Axis, yearly, half yearly, quarterly, monthly
in HDFC and yearly,
half yearly, quarterly and monthly in Tata EIL.  So
my suggestion here would be that you should
not take term insurance on monthly mode.  Because this happens many
times.  Infact
both term insurance and health insurance.  Many
times it happens that due to some reason your
premium gets missed.  It may
not be your fault.  It could be the bank's mistake or some
technical issue due to which the EMI was
not paid or the installment was not paid.
So what will happen?  Your policy will lapse
and you will come to know about it after two-three months when
you realize that my
premium has not been paid.  So after that it becomes
very challenging to revive the policy.
Because the insurance company is providing more cover at lower premium.
So to revive that, there are a lot of
formalities,
a lot of medical tests, you have to be 100%
fit on all fronts.
To get a term insurance
policy both financially and medically.  So what are the inbuilt features?
What are the base benefits of the policy?  Some are riders
, some are base benefits.  Let us first
talk about the inbuilt base benefits.
Death benefit is included in LIC which is available in
term insurance in this policy.
ICICI Protential Plan offers death benefit
plus waiver of premium and early payment
on terminal illness.  Terminal
illness occurs at the terminal stage.  Where the doctor says
that it is the last stage of critical illness
and gives a time duration
that this is how much life you have left.  So that is called
terminal illness.  In that
your sum and or waiver of
premium on permanent disability gets paid out, then
your premium on permanent disability gets waived
off.  Your base benefit is
death benefit in HDFC,
death benefit in Tata.  What optional riders
are available?  This means that
you can avail some riders by paying additional premiums.
Accidental Death Benefit Rider is available in LIC.
In which you get additional sum assured on accidental death.
Over and above the base death
benefit.  Sum
assured is given on the policy amount.  If you take accidental death
benefit.  You can opt for
Accidental Death Benefit and Critical Illness
Benefit in ICSCic.
In Accidental Death Benefit, you choose the additional sum assured
and if the death occurs due to an
accident, then you get the additional sum assured.
Critical illnesses include a list of
20 to 60 illnesses.  If these diseases are
diagnosed then lump sum payment will be made.
Meaning if you have taken a policy with both these riders.
I assume it is a
policy of Rs 50 lakh.  Accidental death
benefit is Rs 50 lakh only.  And 20 lacs is your CI
benefit.  Critical Illness Benefit.  Now
here if death occurs naturally
then 50 lakhs will be given whether it is due to natural or disease.
And if there is an accidental death then
50 lakhs would definitely be given.  50
more lax will be added to it.  Which is your
accidental death some assured.  Now the third
scenario is some critical illness.
Critical Illness: If you suffer from a critical
illness while you are alive, you will be given Rs 20 lakh
if ​​it comes in the list of 20 and
60. If you have rights in whatever you have taken, then
you will get a lump sum payment
and the remaining money will be given to your family on death.
Similarly, Axis Max Life offers
accidental death benefit, critical
illness, return of premium and waiver
of premium.  Here
is a list of 64 critical illnesses that are covered.
So return of premium and waiver
of premium are add ons.  Return of
premium where you get your money back.  By
paying additional premium.  HDFC offers
Accidental Death Benefit, Critical
Illness, Return of Premium, Waiver of
Premium and Critical Illness.  This means that
your premium will be waived off in case of critical illness.
Then there is Tata.  Tata has
accidental death benefit.   There
is Accidental Total and Permanent Disability Benefit.  Critical Plus benefit is
return of premium and waiver of
premium in case of permanent disability.
So these are the five riders available which you
can choose.  There is a special feature I would
like to talk about which is called
Smart Exit Option or Special Exit
Value.  The company gives you this option.
You might have heard the concept of zero cost
term insurance earlier.  The company gives you the option to
take your term insurance
and not pay any money for it.  Meaning
we will refund the money you have paid.
So you have an option to smartly exit
your policy after a few years.  You think
I don't need insurance anymore.   For
what
purpose does a person take term insurance if he has
financial responsibilities.
People are financially dependent on them.  If there are
any liabilities or loans, then
term insurance is taken in these scenarios.
If after some time you feel that
you do not need term insurance.
I don't want to continue.  So
what used to happen earlier was that the term insurance would
end where you stopped it.  Surrender value
was not available.  So this special exit
value will be available.  Everyone's terms and conditions are
different.  Suppose you are 60 years old
and you do not need term insurance.
So you
can get back the premium you paid.  So smart exit
options are available in these policies.
Not available in LIC.  Rest
is available in all four private policies.  You
can exercise.  Your terms and conditions are
different.  And no additional premium has to be paid for this.
So there is zero cost
term insurance.  So this is not a return of
premium.  Return of Premium So
Sure Shot your money comes back.  Sure
shot your money is returned.  For which
you are paying extra money.  You are
paying additional premium.  But here the payout is return
of premium only.  Meaning there is a smart exit
option.  Your premium will be refunded.
After a certain age, you have the option to
surrender the policy and all your
premiums paid will be returned.  Now let's talk about the
death benefit payout option.  Meaning,
how will the beneficiary receive the death benefit.  You will
get lump sum death benefit.  ICICI has Lumpsum
Income, Increasing Income, Lumpsum and Income.  You
can take a combination.  so
what does that mean?  You want your beneficiary to
get the sum assured at one go.  Suppose
you have taken an insurance of Rs 1 crore and you say that you want to get Rs
1 crore at once on your death.
Or you don't want him to earn any income.   It could be that
the spouse and the
beneficiary are not capable of handling the large
amount.  You think that no, ₹1 crore
cannot be handled at once.  So I want that from
now on I am planning that
their income should be created.  Ok?  It can be
income.  It can be increasing income.  You are saying that the
income should keep increasing every year or you should keep some
lumpsum and some income.  You want to get that combination.
Your premium will be
decided accordingly.  So while taking this policy you have to
choose the option.
Both Lumpsum, Lumpsum & Income are available in Axis Maxlite.
Both Lumpsum, Lumpsum & Income
are available in HDFC and Lumpsum, Lumpsum
& Income and Enhanced Sum Assured are also
available in Tata IG.  Pre-policy medical checkup
is mandatory in all these policies.  This means that
you get the policies only after a full body health checkup.
So this is my comparison
of these five plants which I
compared on different parameters, different
ratios, different financial
stability and
talked about their benefits.  Now finally we will
talk about premiums.  So here
I am giving you the basic premium.
I have not included some add-ons here.  You
can customize your policy according to your needs.  So, for example, I have taken a
sum assured of Rs 50 lakh and my age is 31 years.   The person
for whom the policy is being taken is 31 years old.
So I would like to tell you here that the
premiums for male and female are different.  There are
more males and fewer females.
Smoker and non-smoker premiums also
vary.  The premium for a smoker is
higher, while for a non-smoker it
is lower.  So you need to disclose.  So I have taken a
policy pay term of 50 lakhs,
covering me for 39 years i.e. 70 years.  If someone is
taking a policy at the age of 31 years and
wants the cover to be till 70, then these
are the premiums.  You
can customize it as per your requirement.  Can be tailor made.  You
can change the term.  Sum
assured can be changed.  Riders can be added.
Premium paying term can be changed.
And so on.  So I have taken regular pay,
policy tenure 39 regular pay.  So the
premium of LIC Jeevan Amar is Rs 14344.
This is the non-smoker premium and the smoker
premium is Rs 21120.  ICICI's non-smoker
premium is ₹84.  I have taken the premium for
salaried.  Salaried individuals
get a discount in the first year and have to pay the
full premium in the second year.  Some companies have
discounts.  So I am
showing you the premiums for both salaried and self-employed.
We are talking about salaried premiums first.  Same will remain in LIC.  Whether
he is salaried or self-employed.
You will see the difference in other private companies.
[Music] So ICICI
Piden has 84 for salary 31 year old male
non smoker.  The premium for a smoker is 14354
in Axis is 786 and 14160 for a
non-smoker, smoker salary 31 years male,
in HDFC it is 9986 and 17475 and in Tata it is
7430 and ₹169 you
will see that the premiums for females are less, so we have also calculated the premiums for females,
in LIC it is 12100 for a non-
smoker, smoker's annual premium is ₹17512, there is
no GST because
GST has been removed now [Music] ICICI's
is 7178 for a female, salaried female and
122001 for a smoker, salaried female age 31,
in Axis it is 6686 and 1236, in HDFC it is 848 and
₹14853 and in Tata it is 6315 and ₹1258
premium.  We will
look at the premiums for self-employed.  Same as I said in LIC.
But in ICICI you will see that the
premium for self-employed has become ₹9650.
There salary discount is available in the first year.
Only from next year they will
pay the full premium.  So you should understand that in the
first year if you are salaried then your
premium is 84 and if you are self-employed then next
year the premium for salaried will be 9650 only
but for self-employed the premium remains the same
through out.  So the premium is a little higher.
Similarly, we calculated the same for females also.
Get all the companies calculated and it is in
front of you.  So This Was All About Term
Insurance Companies of 2026.  Whatever
question you have, whatever feedback you have, if you
want to connect with our team, please do so.
But before that, do
watch the video of Ultimate Term Insurance
because many of the questions you would
like to ask will be answered there itself.
I am also putting its link below.  You
can connect with us if you want to take policy through us.  You can reach us
through our WhatsApp number.  You
can call.  You can email us and
fill out the Google form.  Our team will
connect you.  And before we go, a
quick reminder, if you have
n't subscribed to our channel yet, please do so.
So that you get the right infection at the right
time.  See you in the next video.  Stay safe.
Take care.  Bye-bye.  [music]
[music]